<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://makoncline.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://makoncline.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-07-19T12:20:24-05:00</updated><id>https://makoncline.com/</id><title type="html">Makon Cline</title><subtitle>Makon Cline</subtitle><entry><title type="html">10,000 Years of Health Care</title><link href="https://makoncline.com/healthsim" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10,000 Years of Health Care" /><published>2018-06-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://makoncline.com/healthInsurance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://makoncline.com/healthsim">Picking a health insurance plan isnt easy.
I think this is by design, to make comparing different plans as difficult as possible for consumers.
An overwhelming amount of information is given for each plan.
Premiums, benifits, deductibles, coinsurance, copay...
In and out of network, health savings accounts, flexiable spending accounts... 

What I want to know is, which plan is the best value?
For each plan, I just want to know three things:
	What's the maximum amount I could possibly pay?
	Whats the minimum amount I could possibly pay?
	What's the average amount I'm likely to pay?

After I have this information, I just need to know my level of risk tolerance and it will be easy to pick a plan.
My company has three different plans for us to decide from.
low monthly premium, high deductible plan, with highest copays for each service, and highest maximum out of pocket.
Medium monthly premium, no deductible plan, with copays for each service, and middle maximum out of pocket.
Higher monthly premium, no deductible plan with lower copays for each service, with lowest maximum out of pocket.

Which is the best for my situation?

It's imposible to know

on first glance, the lowest cost plan seems like a decent option since im young, dont have any dependent family, and don't tend to use many health care services. As long as I continue to not need/use many health care services. This plan would be the cheapest.
But, at what level of use with the more expensive plans save me money?

The middle plan has a good balance of monthly premium and lower cost co pay for services, but the maximum out of pocket is a few thousand higher than the more expansive plan. If I use some regular health services, this plan seems like it could be the best balance in price to features. But again, where is the level of use that this plan will save me money?

The last plan is expensive compared to the other two, but the copay for services is almost half, and the the maximum out of pocket is a few thousand dollars lower. This would obviously be the best plan if I know im going to be using my health care services frequently. But again, what amount of use makes it worth the extra money per month?

There is no way to know what kind of health care you will need before it happens.
You could get sick unexpectedly many times in a year.
you could have a single accident that puts you in the hospital for a few days or requires surgery.
You could need 10 surgeries, who knows?..

while it would be impossible to forecast the exact number of times you would use each service during the plan year, it would be easy to come up with a minimum and maximum number of times you might use  each service.

I ask made the following statment for each healthcare service group.
I am 95% confident that I will use this service between X and Y times.
With X being the absolute minimum I Could possibly use a service.
With Y being the absolute maximum i could possibly use a service.

My thinking for most of the categories is a follows, using times seeing a primary care physician as an example:
I have had years where I havent been to My PCP at all, so zero isnt a crazy number for my minimum.
But this year i know that i will at least being going one time for my annual physical. So my minimum  number of visits is one.
The maximum is a little more difficult.
What if I come down with a helth problem that require frequent visits?
If that happens, lets say i have to see my primary car physician three times in the first month of the diagnosis, then once a month afterwards.
This puts my maximum number of uses at 14.
Now, I've been health all my life, so I dont actually think I will be going to My primary care physician 14 times in a year, even though its possible.

I need a way to simulate a year of me going to my primary care doctor.
I could take a random number, between my minimum and maximum expected use  and use it to calculate exactly how much I will pay in health care on each plan for the year.
Now were getting somewhere!
If i get my minimum and maximum use for each health service category, i can simulate an entire year of health care and know the exact cost!

So thats great, but...
some years the random number  may all be very high...
some years they may all be very low...
This would scew my insurance plan selection
I could wind up buying an expansive plan when i dont need it
or i could wind up with a cheap plan that winds up costing me a ton of money.

But what if i did this simulation 10 times and averaged the results?
The extremes would average out, giving me a closer picture to what im likely to spend.

So then what if i do it 100 times instead?
I get a better average, but is it accurate? Not sure.

But im pretty confident that if i could simulate 10,000 years of health service usage for each plan, I would wind up with a pretty godd picture of the minimum, maximum, and average i can be expected to spend with each of the plan choices.

So how can i do this? Easiest way to at least test the concept is with microsoft excel.

I've set  up a spread sheet to do exactly what i detailed above.
I input a minimum and maximum number of time i can expect to use each health service.
I pick a random number between the minimum and maximum
I multiply the random number by the price of the service
Then add up the total
Then i repeat this 10,000 times
I take the lowest total value as the minimum I could to spend
The highest total value as the maximum I could spend
And then the average of the 10,000 totals is the average amount im likely to spend in a year with each plan.

Lets look at my companies health care plans as an exmaple
***screenshot of three plans with cost of services for each***
Screenshot of random values added up to to costs</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Picking a health insurance plan isnt easy. I think this is by design, to make comparing different plans as difficult as possible for consumers. An overwhelming amount of information is given for each plan. Premiums, benifits, deductibles, coinsurance, copay... In and out of network, health savings accounts, flexiable spending accounts...</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fisherman and the Banker</title><link href="https://makoncline.com/fish" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fisherman and the Banker" /><published>2018-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://makoncline.com/fish</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://makoncline.com/fish">&lt;section&gt;
&lt;p&gt; I'm not sure where this parable originated, but I like the version from &lt;a href=&quot;https://joshkaufman.net/about-josh-kaufman/&quot;&gt;Josh Kaufman's&lt;/a&gt; book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://personalmba.com/&quot;&gt;The Personal MBA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once, a powerful executive went on vacation — his first in fifteen years. As he was exploring a pier in a small coastal fishing village, a tuna fisherman docked his boat. As the Fisherman lashed his boat to the pier, the Executive complimented him on the size and quality of his fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How long did it take you to catch these fish?” the Executive asked.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Only a little while,” the Fisherman replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why don’t you stay out longer and catch more?” the Executive asked.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have enough to support my family’s needs,” said the Fisherman.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But,” asked the Executive, “what do you do with the rest of your time?”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fisherman replied, “I sleep late, fish a little, play with my children, take a siesta with my wife, and stroll into the village each evening where I sip wine and play guitar with my friends. I have a full and busy life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Executive was flabbergasted. “I’m a Harvard MBA, and I can help you. You should spend more time fishing. With the proceeds, you could buy a bigger boat. A bigger boat would help you catch more fish, which you could sell to buy several boats. Eventually, you’d own an entire fleet.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Instead of selling your catch to a middleman you could sell directly to the consumers, which would improve your margins. Eventually, you could opening your own factory, so you’d control the product, the processing and the distribution. Of course, you’d have to leave this village and move to the city so you could run your expanding enterprise.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fisherman was quiet for a moment, then asked, “How long would this take?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fifteen, twenty years. Twenty-five, tops.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Then what?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Executive laughed. “That’s the best part. When the time is right, you’d take your company public and sell all of your stock. You’d make millions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Millions? What would I do then?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Executive paused for a moment. “You could retire, sleep late, fish a little, play with your children, take a siesta with your wife, and stroll into the village each evening to sip wine and play the guitar with your friends.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pictures/fish.jpg&quot; class=&quot;img-fluid rounded&quot;&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I'm not sure where this parable originated, but I like the version from Josh Kaufman's book, The Personal MBA.</summary></entry></feed>